Benjamin Franklin Papers Part 13 -- Miscellaneous Franklin Materials 1640-1791 Mss.B.F85inventory13
American Philosophical Society
- Miscellaneous Franklin Materials
  - to [Ferdinand] Grand., 1778 June 3; L.S. 1p.; de Breteuil, Baron. Vienna
    Mr. [William] Lee presented the latter's letter of introduction. Will do all in his power to make his stay in Vienna agreeable. Has recommended Mr. Michel Comyn's application for Consul at Marseilles to Mr. [William] Lee. Requests M. Grand to use his influence with Dr. Franklin and the other deputies to secure the appointment for Mr. Comyn.
  - to [John] Adams, Paris., 1778 June 15; A.L.S. 3p.; Sayre, Stephen. Copenhagen
    Attended Mr. [William] Lee to Berlin, at the public expense, and there he was told that he would no longer be considered in that service or to expect the least support from the Commissioners, whether he return to Paris or not. Decided to remain at Berlin. Wrote to his friends in Congress and though the Commissioners had many letters sent to their care for him, they did not forward them or give any reasons for with-holding them. Requests him to learn the cause of this and to state it to him with candor.
  - to [Ferdinand] Grand, Paris., 1778 June 16; A.L. 1p.; Hutton, James
    Expressing great affection for M. Grand and his family; begs him to tell his friend [Franklin?] that he has not yet received the promised paper which he begs to have sent him as soon as possible.
  - Miscellaneous Papers, Printed Diss. 4p.; The Treatment of Elie Trigant, surnamed Jean Bart, by the English and Grenezeys. Guernseys
    (In French. From the Passe Port de St. Malo. 1778 June 17.)
  - Miscellaneous Papers, 1778 June 22; D.S. 2p.; Castle, Joy
    Oath of allegiance to the United States.
  - Miscellaneous Papers, 1778 June 23 and August 10; D.S. 2p.; Amiel, Peter. Passy
  - to ----- Gamba., 1778 June 23; A.L.S. 1p.; Hartley, Samuel. London
    With reference to the latter's application for the Consulship at Dunkerque.
  - Miscellaneous Papers, 1778 June 23; D.S. 1p.; Moore, William. Passy
  - to Messrs. J[onathan] Nesbitt and Co., 1778 June 24; L.S. 1p.; Stewart, Stephen. West River, MaryLand
    Recommends to them Mr. James Cheston.
  - to M. Greg[o]rio Alvarez de Verjusty, Cadiz., 1778 June 26; L.S. 1p.; Kenguer, Y. Bertrand. Brest
    On his arrival in France sends duplicate of account sent by letter from Boston. Obtained release of merchandise seized; his ship also was restored to him. Carried his suit before the different law courts of the United States, at an expense of 6,125 livres. Does not know whether the other shippers, whose goods were seized, are willing to go to the same expense.
  - Miscellaneous Papers, 1778 June 27; D.S. 2p.; Townsend, Solomon. Passy
  - to Arthur Lee., 1778 June 29; L.S. 3p.; Puchelberg and Co. L'Orient
    In accordance with instructions given to [Francis] Coffyn, of Dunkerque, have claimed three sailors from Boston, who were amongst a batch of 43 English prisoners brought in by the French frigate "l'Oiseau." Commander of frigate granted their request and ordered the three sailors to be delivered over to the United States frigate now at Brest.
  - to Capt. [Robert] Niles., [1778 June.]; Mem. 1p.; James Watson and Nathan Strong
    As he is about to sail for France, they gave him instructions as to purchasing printing type.
  - Miscellaneous Papers, 1778 July 1; D.S. 4p.; Penet, D'Acosta frères and Cie. Nantes
    Contract by which the latter are to furnish certain supplies of arms, ammunition and other like articles to the State of Virginia, under certain terms and conditions.
  - to [Ferdinand] Grand, Paris., 1778 July 1; A.L.S. 2p.; Comyn, Michel. Marscilles
    On the subject of his appointment as Consul for the United States. Refers to services he rendered to M. [François] de la Baume and Count Pula(w)ski and to Mr. [Silas] Deane.
  - to John Wetherhead., 1778 July 1; L.S. 3p.; Williamos, Charles. London
    Admiral [Augustus] Keppel took two or three French frigates, but as he allowed their merchantmen to pass unmolested and is returned to Portsmouth with all his fleet, it does not seem as if they were yet in good earnest. Sends a duplicate of a bill of lading for some little comforts which his friend Mr. Masserett shipped for him last May.
  - to Captain [Robert] Niles., 1778 July 4; A.L.S. 2p.; Simpson, Thomas. Brest
    Asks him to inform the Commissioners of the unjust treatment he received from Capt. [John Paul] Jones, and that when Capt. Jones appeared desirous of settling the matter, he proposed that Capt. Jones give him the liberty to return to America and go into the service of his country, but Captain Jones desired a letter from him stating that his conduct has given Capt. Jones reasons to treat him in the manner he had done, and even promised him a command should he do that; when he refused, Jones declared he would do everything possible against him.
  - to John Adams, Passy., 1778 July 4; A.L.S. 2p.; MacCreery, William. Nantes
    Announcing the arrival of the Saratoga with letters and packets; one to him, dated March 27th, details the movements of Generals Washington and Clinton at that time. Men-of-war have all left Chesapeake Bay. The people so happy at the publication of the Treaty, that they are indulging themselves with dancing.
  - Miscellaneous Papers, 1778 July 6; 2p.; Partial List of the Crew of the "Angelica."
    Taken by the "Andromeda" and imprisoned at Forton.
  - to ------- Gourlade, Paris., 1778 July 8; A.L.S. 2p.; Moylan, James. L'Orient
    On arrival here of the frigate "Boston," Puchelberg and Co. spread reports that they were going to attend to the vessel's business, as Schweighauser and Co., of Nantes, had been appointed Agents for American vessels. Could not at first belive this, as he had not received any counter orders from the Commissioners at Passy. Wrote to Schweighauser and Co. who replied that they had been appointed Agents. To avoid disputes will give up all claims, but asks him to make representations to M.[Le Ray] de Chaumont on the subject.
  - to J[oh]n Emery, 1778 July 10; L. 3p.; --------, --------. San Sebastin
    With reference to the seizure and condemnation of the ship "Britannia" by the Spanish authorities. Urges him to write to Dr. Franklin and get him to use his good offices in the matter.
  - Miscellaneous Papers, 1778 July 10; D. 2p.; The Chamber of Commerce. Dunkerque
    Certificates concerning François Jean Coffyn, ship broker and interpreter at Dunkerque.
  - to Robert Paper and Francis Kinlock, Charles Town, South Carolina., 1778 July 13; A.L.S. 2p.; Colleton, Margaret. London
    Alarmed at a report that the proprietors of estates in South Carolina wihtout distinction, are required to appear there within a given time, upon pain of confiscation of their property or other grievous penalty; owing to her being a helpless woman, over seventy-five years old, it is impossible for her to obey the terms of this decree. The two estates left her by her husband, John Colleton; has received no remittances since 1775; begs them to use every means to protect her property.
  - to John Adams, Passy., 1778 July 15; A.L.S. 1p.; Lee, Arthur. Chaillot
    Too unwell to stir out. Begs that the papers relative to Mr. [Musco] Livingston's sailing may be brought to him for his signature.
  - to [Ferdinand] Grand, Paris., 1778 July 17; A.L.S. 3p.; Comyn, Michel. Marscilles
    Thanking him for exerting his influence with Messrs. Franklin, Lee and Adams, in his behalf. Sends an application, to be endorsed by them and transmitted to Congress, with reference to his appointment as Consul.
  - to [Jean Baptiste] Le Roy., 1778 July 18; A.L.S. 1p.; de Guémadeuc, Baudoin
    Begging him to obtain from Dr. Franklin a letter of recommendation in favor of M. Lalande Robinot, merchant of St. Brieuc, who is in the act of despatching a vessel for the United States; he is worthy of every courtesy.
  - to [Edward] Bancroft, Paris., 1778 July 19; A.L.S. 1p.; Kendall, Joseph. Nantes
    Begs him to seal and deliver the enclosed, after he has perused it.
  - to M. Houdin, Paris., 1778 July 26.; Mem. 3p.; De Martigny, M. Captain of Infantry
    Concerning Houdin's brother who is serving as a Lieutenant in the United States troops. Note with reference to M. [Gayault] de Boisbetrand's imprisonment and hardships.
    A. E. by Dr. Franklin. That his sufferings being made known to the Congress, it will be very agreeable to them to understand that he has met with consideration here on that account.
  - to [Ferdinand] Grand., 1778 July 28; A.L.S. 3p.; Comyn, Michel. Vienna
    With reference to the appointment of Michel Comyn as Consul for the United States at Marseilles.
  - Miscellaneous Papers, 1778 July 30; D. 1p.; Prince de Montbarrey Minister of War. Versailles
    Certificate as to the military services and record of M. [Flobergue de] la Rocatelle, an officer of engineers.
  - to ------ Le Févre., 1778 July 30; A. Dr. of L. 1p.; Franklin, William Temple. Passy
    Thanking him for his good wishes.
  - to Capt. [Thomas] Simpson., 1778 July 30; A.L.S. 2p.; Strongham, William. Brig "Patience," Brest Road
    Captured by the "Ranger." Is sixty years of age and is being sent to prison. Begs him to speak to the American Agents in his favor, that he may be set free.
  - to [Le Ray de] Chaumont, Passy., 1778 July 31; A.L. 1p.; Vaughan, Benjamin. London
    Desires M. Chaumont to deliver the enclosed scraps of paper to his venerable friend who always carries on his nose, spectacles, and on his shoulders, kingdoms.
  - to Arthur Lee., 1778 August 4 to November 19; L.S. 10p.; Penet, D'Acosta frères and Cie. Nantes
    Letters concerning an order for supplies for the State of Virginia given by Mr. Lee, and the dispute over alleged delay in delivery. Replies to new conditions or terms proposed by Mr. Lee which they reject in detail, giving specific reasons therefor.
  - to Jonathan Williams, [Jr.], Passy., 1778 August 14; A.L.S. 1p.; De Court, de Sorlut. Paris
    Desires to know if his uncle, Mr. [John] Williams, of London, and Colonel Boyd are arrived in France.
  - to [Ferdinand] Grand, Paris., 1778 August 14; A.L.S. 3p.; Comyn, Michel. Marscilles
    With reference to his appointment as Consul at Marseilles. Has heard from Vienna that the United States Commissioners at Paris, have received powers from Congress to appoint Consuls. Alludes to previous services he rendered to the American cause and cites a few instances.
    - Miscellaneous Papers, 1778 July 26; Diss. 3p.; Valltravers, Johann Rodolph. Rocall
      Memoir on the natural relationship or resemblance existing between the Thirteen United States of North America and the Thirteen Cantons of Switzerland. Are both Allies of France. Their community of interests. Reasons why friendly alliance should be made by the United States and Switzerland.
  - to Abraham Whipple., 1778 August 18; L.S. 1p.; Jones, Capt. John Paul. Brest
    Requests him to call a Court Martial for the trial of Lieutenant Thomas Simpson with whose conduct he has been and is unsatisfied.
  - to Rodolph Valltravers., 1778 August 19; L.S. 4p.; Christopher de Graffenried, Baron of Worb. Castle fo Worb
    Enclosing the memorial which he desires him to forward to Dr. Franklin; the difficulties he has experienced in obtaining information of his estates in America. The memorial gives an account of Baron de Graffenried's ancestors setting in America and receiving grants of land there; desires information on important points connected with the present ownership.
  - to John Paul Jones., 1778 August 19; L.S. 2p.; Whipple, Abraham. Brest
    Received his letter requesting him to summon a Court Martial for the trail of Lieutenant Thomas Simpson. Informs him of the impossibility of calling a Court Martial and also acquaints him fully with his sentiments on the subject.
  - Miscellaneous Papers, 1778 August 19; D.S. 2p.; William Hill Sergeant and John Hans Delap
    Bond given in connection with a letter of marque issued by the United States to John Hill Sergeant of the brig "Dispatch," of Virginia, and John Hans Delap, merchant of Bordeaux.
  - Miscellaneous Papers, 1778 August 20; D.S. 1p.; Woodford, Thomas. Passy
  - to Isaac Sears, 1778 August 25; L.S. 9p.; Sayre, Stephen. Copenhagen
    Letter printed in the English papers of August 16th, 1779. Original said to have been seized on the vessel "Delaware" going from Mayestrand to Philadelphia.
    Opportunities for trade in Danish and Norwegian ports for American vessels. Secure from capture by English vessels. Would be allowed to take prizes and have them sold. Asks his correspondent to send a vessel to him, with a cargo of tobacco or other goods. Vessel could be sold after cargo is disposed of. Crew would then be put on board a new vessel which he is having built on original plans of his own. Is to be different from the old style of vessels. Will be able to outstrip any English war vessels. Advantages and profits to be derived from this plan. Would have returned to Boston long ago; feared however to be taken prisoner by the English and kept in jail until the end of the war. Surprised that his friends in America have received no letters from him since he left England. Wrote over one hundred. Some were to have been forwarded by the American Commissioners in Paris. Suspects them of some trickery in the matter. Accuses Dr. Franklin of keeping letters which he received for him and of not replying to him when he writes about the matter. Is indignant at this campering with other people's correspondence. No excuse for it whatever. Thinks there is jealousy amongst Franklin's "encourage."
  - Miscellaneous Papers, 1778 August 29; D.S. 2p.; Nuttle, Samuel. Passy
  - to [Ferdinand] Grand, Paris., 1778 August 30; L.S. 3p.; Eml. and Ns. Weis et fils. La Rochelle
    Wish to be appointed Consular Agent for the United States at the above port.
  - to [John] Adams, 1778 September 2; A.L.S. p.; Rolandeau, -----. Paris
    His present grievous situation; encloses a list of articles which he lost, when captured on his way back to America; begs that he may he sent to Nantes, to take passage for the United States.
  - to Sir George Grand., 1778 September 3; A.L.S. 2p.; Dumas, C.G.F.
    Concerning a projected loan of 700,000 florins on behalf of the United States.
  - to Sir George Grand, Amsterdam., 1778 September 2; A.L.S. 2p.; Dumas, C.G.F.
    Further details concerning the projected loan.
  - Miscellaneous Papers, 1778 September 4; D.S. 1p.; John Walter Fletcher, James Johnson, George Carl Voss. Passy
  - to Jonathan Williams, Jr., 1778 September 6; L. 2p.; Vaughan, Benjamin. London
    Inquiring about the case of Mr. [John] Boylston who offers to take the oath and give security before going to America.
  - to [François, Barbé] de Marbois, Philadelphia., 1787 September 7; A.L.S. 2p.; Legaux, Peter. Spring Mill.
    Requests him to forward a package by the French packet boat which sails on the 10th.
  - Miscellaneous Papers, 1778 September 8; D.S. 1p.; Montgomery, Robert. Passy
  - to [Ferdinand] Grand, Paris., 1778 September 8; A.L.S. 1p.; Hutton, James. Calais
    Description of his journey to Holland; wrote Dr. Franklin about a passport he desired for some Moravians who are going to Pennsylvania, and requested to know the name of the vessel carrying General Montgomery's monument to America, in order, if possible, to insure its safety. Desries to know whether Mr. Gayault de Boisbertran has arrived safely in France.
  - to The Prince De Nassau[-Siegen]., 1778 September 9; A.L.S. 3p.; Jones, Capt. John Paul. Brest
    Dr. Franklin informs him that M. [Antoine Raymond Jean Gualbert Gabriel] de Sartine is sorry he (Jones) is with Comte [Louis Gillouet] d'Orvilliers, and concludes that he lost the opportunity by his stay at l'Orient. An account of himself since he was requested to remain in France by M. de Sartine. Account of the "Epervier" which was reputed to be a vessel of very large dimensions, with 16 guns and of superior swiftness. His situtation appears a mystery and he concludes that he has fallen a sacrifice to some intrigue of State.
  - to The Continental Congress., 1778 September 10; A.L. 7p.; Williams, Jonathan Jr.
    The nature of his duties under the Commissioners; the accusations of Mr. A[rthur] Lee, and his own defense; sends his accounts and begs that they may be examined and settled.
  - to Capt. [Jacques] Le Maire., 1778 September 14; Dr. of L. 1p.; Lee, Arthur. Chaillot
    Has ordered M. [John D.] Schweighauser to advance him a certain sum, which is the very last sou he can afford to give him for his expenses.
  - to The Continental Congress., 1778 September 18; D.S. 1p.; Mons, Samuel Stanley, baron and -----, baroness de. Amsterdam
    Petition relative to his estates near Boston and Charleston.
  - to Arthur Lee., 1778 September 19; L. 4p.; Le Maire de Gimel, Jacques
    Concerning the various articles he has been commissioned to purchase for Virginia; their price and the best means of getting them to America.
  - to [John] Adams., 1778 September 19; A.L.S. 1p.; Austin, Jonathan Loring. Passy
    Refers the enclosed letter for the Commissioners, entirely to his approval.
  - Miscellaneous Papers, 1778 September 21; D.S. 4p.; Chevallié, Pierre François
    Statement of his account with the State of Virginia.
  - to Arthur Lee., 1778 September 22; A.L.S. 2p.; Le Maire de Gimel, Jacques. Nantes
    Acknowledging the receipt of a certain sum which, however, is not sufficient to cover his expenses. The precautions necessary to insure the safe arrival of the articles in Virginia.
  - to [Benjamin] Vaughan., 1778 September 24; A. Dr. of L. 1p.; Franklin, William Temple. Passy
    With reference to Mr. [John] Boylston's admission to America.
  - to [Matthew] Ridley., 1778 September 30; L. 1p.; Norton, George
    Concerning a sum he advanced certain of his friends in order to defray their expenses, and the easiest way to have the said sum paid back. (Copy.)
  - to [Ferdinand] Grand, Paris., 1778 October 9; A.L.S. 1p.; Hutton, James. Paris
    Desiring to know if M. d'Anhic's friend has arrived in Paris. Concerning a passport for some friends which he desired to obtain from Dr. Franklin.
  - to Edw[ar]d Bancroft., 1778 October 9; A.L.S. 1p.; Jones, Capt. John Paul. Brest
    Begs him to show the enclosed letter to Dr. Franklin and, if approved, to deliver it.
  - Miscellaneous Papers, 1778 October 13; D.S. 1p.; Barnard, Tristram
    Oath to settle in America for life.
  - Miscellaneous Papers, [1778.] October 13; D.S. 1p.; Barnard, Tristram. Passy
  - to Louis XVI., 1778 October 19; A.L.S. 4p.; Jones, Capt. John Paul. Brest
    Informed by Dr. Franklin that M. [Antoine Raymond Jean Gualbert Gabriel] de Sartine, with his approbation, determined to give him command of the "Indien." Was to have taken command immediately but found that the ship would not be ready until the September Equinox. The American Plenipotentiaries proposed that he go home, but M. de Sartine requested that he remain in Europe. Proposed various plans and had several armaments assigned to him but everyone has fallen to nothing. Informed Congress to reserve no command for him. Is regarded everywhere as disgraced officer. Wrote to M. de Sartine and Prince de Nassau but received no replies. Is persuaded that His Majesty will not disregard his situation nor suffer him to remain any longer in that insupportable disgrace.
  - to La Duchesse de Chartres., 1778 October 19; A.L.S. 2p.; Jones, Capt. John Paul. Brest
    Informs her that M. [Antoine Raymond Jean Gualbert Gabriel] de Sartine proposed to bestow on him a very honorable command and that he requested the American Plenipotentiaries that he be permitted to remain in Europe. Furnished the Minister with a number of plans which he approved, for private expeditions, but though various armanents were proposed to be put under his command, yet everyone has fallen to nothing. Has been trifled with for five months and valuable opportunities are lost. He wrote to Congress to reserve no command or him in America, and having no command in Europe he is regarded everywhere as an officer in disgrace. Reason for taking any command. Has written the enclosed letter to His Majesty which he asks her to present. Would be extremely happy to succeed through her influence.
  - Miscellaneous Papers, 1778 October 21; A.D.S. Cha[rle]s Thomson, Sec[retary]. 1p.; The Continental Congress
    Giving leave of absence and the thanks of Congress to the Marquis de la Fayette and directing that the Minister Plenipotentiary at the Court of Versailles present him, in the name of the United States, with sword with proper devices.
    Printed in the Journals of Congress, Philadelphia [1779], IV, 612.
  - Miscellaneous Papers, 1778 October 22; D.S. Cha[rle]s Thomson, sec[retar]y. 1p.; The Continental Congress
    Respecting a good agreement among the foreign representatives of the Congress.
  - to [Sir George] Grand, Amsterdam., 1778 October 27; A.L.S. 1p.; Hutton, James
    Wrote to Dr. Franklin and requested a small favor of him, also desired to know the name of the vessel carrying General Montgomery's statue to America; no answer has come to these questions.
  - to [Samuel] Huntington., 1778 November 6; A.L.S. 1p.; Holker, Jean. Boston
    Entreats him to furnish M. Vestas de Gassies with everything necessary for the poor French prisoners that are in Norwich under his care. Will pay everything he may advance.
  - to M. de Fontinet., 1778 November 17; A.L.S. 1p.; Hirschberg, Charles de. Paris.
    With reference to a sum of money unlawfully received and retaine by Mr. [Arthur] Lee's man-servant.
  - to ------ [Le] Baron., 1778 November 17; L.S. 2p.; Prince, Job. "The Concord," off Dieppe
    Arrived on this coast from off Cape Artifer and retook a shalle belonging to this port, from two English privateers. Heard that he transacts their agency business at Dieppe and would like to know in what manner he can assist him. Proposes cruising northward to intercept outward and inward bound ships of the enemy. His ship resembles the English ship "Childers." Intends getting as close to the English coast as possible in order to get information about their fishing and pilot boats. Asks him to send some refreshments for his ship's company. Asks for draughts of this and the English coasts.
  - to [Anquetil] Duperron., 1778 November 18; A.L.S. 1p.; Delacolonge, ------. Lyons
    Reply to Dr. Franklin's note. Requests his correspondent to procure him the appointment as Agent for the United States, at Lyons.
  - to John Paul Jones, Brest., 1778 November 20; L.S. 1p.; Walsh, John, and other Prisoners. "Patience," Brig, Brest Road
    Request him to deliver the enclosed, as directed, and to use his interest in their favor.
  - Miscellaneous Papers, 1778 November 21; Engraved D.S. 1p.; Gaspard Castagni, Agent of the French Navy. Rotterdam
    Certificate to Jean Dian, of Boston, an ex-prisoner of war in England, for safe passage.
  - to Jonathan Williams, Jr., 1778 December 5; A.L. 1p.; Vaughan, Benjamin. London
    Sends a paper from Michael Lovell, partner of Thomas Oliver, and recommends their firm as a good west India house.
  - to M. Fizeaux., 1778 December 7; A.L.S. 2p.; Capellen tot den Pol, Joan Derk van der. Zwolle
    Begs him to send the enclosed packet to Dr. Franklin, which contains the copy of his answer to the Governor of Connecticut. The zeal with which he pursues the negotiation for Congress.
  - to [Lieut.-Col. Antoine Félix] Wuibert., 1778 December 9; A.L.S. 1p.; Lunt, Joseph. Forton Prison
    Requesting him, when he arrives in France, to tell Dr. Franklin that he (Lunt) is one of the oldest prisoners, and that his two sons be with him.
  - Miscellaneous Papers, 1778 December 23; D.S. Cha[rle]s Thomson, Sec[retar]y. 1p.; The Continental Congresss